Guide to the Blanche Harding Sewall Papers MS 431
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Blanche Harding Sewall Papers
1847-1959
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Sewall, Blanche Harding
MS 431
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, college materials, pamphlets and programs, materials related to the construction of Sewall residence and the Sewall's Japan trip. The dates for this collection range from 1847 to 1959 with the bulk of the material ranging from 1935 to 1948.
Biographical / Historical
Blanche Harding Sewall (Mrs. Cleveland Sewall) was a native of Fort Worth, Texas and attended Rice Institute with the class of 1917. She was an artist, philanthropist and, as a patron of the arts, a founding member of the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston. She organized a private foundation, the Library of Arts. At her husband's death in 1942, she assumed operations of his wholesale grocery company, Carson Sewall & Co. Marine Division. As a memorial to her husband, she donated funds for the construction of a building for the Rice campus, Sewall Hall. Mrs. Sewall died on May 28, 1973, in Houston. Funds from her estate provided for the Andrew Hays Buchanan Professorship and the Noah Harding Professorship at Rice. Andrew Hays Buchanan was her maternal grandfather, and Noah Harding was her paternal grandfather. The Sewall residence, designed by Ralph Adams Cram in the Mediterranean Renaissance style in 1925, was left to Rice University. Blanche Harding Sewall was awarded Rice's Gold Medal posthumously in 1973.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, college materials, pamphlets and programs, materials related to the construction of the Sewall residence, and the Sewall's trip to Japan. The dates for this collection range from 1847 to 1959 with the bulk of the material ranging from 1935 to 1948.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Accruals
No future additions are expected for this material.
Acquisitions Information
The bulk of the materials were received in 1974 from Texas Commerce Bank, executor of Mrs. Sewall's estate. Additional materials were received in 1988. Correspondence between Blanche Harding Sewall and Cleveland Sewall was added in 2020.
Related Materials
Additional information about Blanche Harding Sewall may be found in the following information files located in the Woodson Research Center: Blanche Harding Sewall; Sewall Hall; Sewall House; and Cleveland Sewall Hall dedication, 1971, photo album.
Index Terms
Subjects
Gardening; Gardening -- Societies, etc.; Clubs -- Japan; Philanthropists; Art
Document Types
drawings (visual works); postcards; souvenirs; family papers; photographs; corrrespondence; personal papers; pamphlets
Places
Japan; Texas
Subjects (Persons)
Sewall, Blanche Harding; Sewall, Blanche Harding; Cram, Ralph Adams; Sewall family
Subjects (Corporations)
Sewall House; Garden Club of America
- Series I. Correspondence, 1913-1949, n.d.
  Scope and Contents note
  26 letters arranged in chronological order beginning with the earliest and ending with the undated letters.
  - G.C. Frakes to Blanche, Jan. 2, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles A. Lott to Cleveland Sewall, April 9, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Allen C. Hutchinson to Mrs. Claude Thompson, April 19, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. A.C. Hutchinson to Mrs. James Mercer Blaine, April 19, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nita and Lucille to M/M Cleveland Sewall, April 19, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charlie [CJK] to M/M Eric Brashay, April 21, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dr./Mrs Joseph Mullen to M/M Cleveland Sewall, April 26, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Campbell Sewall to M/M Cleveland Sewall, May 13, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Emily Evans to Blanche, May 13, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - K. Mikimoto to M/M Cleveland Sewall, May 13, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Horton to Mrs. Sewall, May 14, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Summer Palace Co. to Mrs. Sewall, June 8, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - T. Komatsu to M/M Cleveland Sewall, Sept. 10, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Douglas L. Dunbar to Mrs. Sewall, Nov.16, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kaoruko Matsunuya to M/M Cleveland Sewall, c. 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - M/M Takashi Komatsu to M/M Cleveland Sewall, Dec. 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Sewall to Dr. Roy Harris, Jan. 19, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Paula Mechau to Mrs. Sewall, Feb. 25, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Roy Harris to Mrs. Sewall, March 1, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Roy Harris to Mrs. Sewall (extract), March 1, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Johana Harris to Mrs.Sewall, Dec. 30, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Roy Harris to Mrs. Sewall, June 11, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Louise Brown to M/M Cleveland Sewall (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - M/M Hardie Robinson to M/M Cleveland Sewall (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Johana Harris to Mrs. Sewall, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - H. On- to Mrs. Sewall, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Printed Matter, 1884-1936, n.d.
  - College Materials, 1884-1886 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Texas centennial, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Misc. booklets, notes, etc. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III. Japan Trip
  - General Information (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Travel papers and receipts (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Garden Club of America bulletins, program (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sightseeing, shopping information (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sightseeing, shopping information (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Invitations (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Souvenir postcards (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Japanese newsclippings (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Menus (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hotel New Grand, Yokohama (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Calling cards (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photograph album (Box 2)
  - A Photographic Diary of the Visit of the Garden Club of America to Japan (Box 3)
  - Gardens in Japan Visited by the Garden Club of America, May 1935 (Box 3)
  - Kyoto, 1934 (Box 3)
- Series IV. Sewall residence, 1847-1929, n.d.
  Copies of plats, correspondence related to the building, specifications, building contracts, transcripts of a lawsuit, drawings and photographs. Arranged in chronological order beginning with the earliest and ending with undated materials.
  - Copies of plats of 3 land surveys in Harris Co., 1847, 1861, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Plat of Country Club Estates (River Oaks) [1924?, 1927?] Original Covenants and Restrictions in Country Club Estates Additions (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re:building rights in Broadacres, March 10, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Specifications for excavation, foundations, cut stone ... painting, Aug. 18, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Specifications for heating, pp. 1-25, Aug. 28, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Specifications for plumbing, Sept. 11, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Specifications for electrical work, Sept. 16, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Specifications for alterations in study room, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Contract for plumbing and heating, Cleveland Sewall and Lee Rogerson, Dec. 10, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Contract between Cleveland Sewall and Russell Brown Co., 1924 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Contract for electrical, Cleveland Sewall and Jacob Bros., Jan. 12, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence re:work orders (Russell Brown Co.) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Russell Brown Co. weekly payroll statements, 1925-26 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Transcripts of Russell Brown Co. vs. Cleveland Sewall, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Transcript of Russell Brown Co. vs. Cleveland Sewall, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous drawings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of bathrooms and kitchen, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Plot plan of Sewall residence, Aug. 29, 1924 (Map-drawer Map case, drawers 31-32)
  - House plans
- Series V. Cleveland Sewall and Blanche Harding Sewall Correspondence, 1910-1919
  - Correspondence, 1910-1919 (Box 4, Folder 16)